A Guide to the Augusta County (Va.) Business Records, 1789-1908
Library of Virginia
- Alanson Harris Blacksmith Ledgers and Daybook, 1839-1867, 5 volumes
  - Alanson Harris Blacksmith Ledgers, 1860-1862; 1860-1867
    Record the accounts of individual customers. Information found in each account includes the date, type of service provided, and the monies debited or credited to the account. Services provided included shoeing horses, sharpening tools, and repairing wagons and carriages. Also, the back of the volume dated 1860-1862 was used as a daybook for September 1861 to December 1861 with transactions recorded on an almost daily basis. Each entry includes customer name, service provided, and the amount charged for the service.
    - Alanson Harris Blacksmith Ledger, 1860-1862
    - Alanson Harris Blacksmith Ledger, 1860-1867
- Henry Holloway Plantation Ledger, 1796-1810, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Henry Holloway was a plantation owner in Amherst County, Virginia. He died on 12 June 1810.
  Scope and Content: Henry Holloway Plantation Ledger, 1796-1810, records the business activities of the Holloway family's plantation and the personal financial activities of Henry Holloway. The ledger records the accounts of individuals, estates, and businesses that Holloway managed or with whom he conducted business. Each account lists transactions in chronological order, and each transaction includes the date, the type of transactions, and monies debited and credited.
  The accounts connected with the plantation document purchases made for items such as trees, oxen, horses, sugar, and coffee. Several accounts include a listing for the hiring of enslaved individuals; although, no detail is provided as to what type of work they performed on the plantation. There are also entries for the plantation overseer that concern his wages and providing him his share of wheat and corn. Holloway also kept records of the quantities of wheat seeded, used by the family, and sold.
  The personal financial accounts of Henry Holloway document the individuals and businesses with which Holloway conducted business. Many of the accounts detail Holloway's family expenses and document tuition paid and purchases of clothing and books. There are several account entries that detail the settlement of the estate of Robert Holloway who died around 1802. Holloway also helped to support his sister Betsey Yancey, wife of Robert Yancey. Her account entry includes the following note written by Holloway: "It is impossible for the Writer to say how unhappy he has been made from the imprudence of Capt. Robert Yancey. He has brought a wife and children to want from his drinking as well as gambling. The above articles is given to a sister who is in want of much more, and I wish I had it in my power to give it."
  Also see: Augusta County Chancery Cause, Norvell Spencer vs. Exr. of Henry Holloway, 1814-085. Avaible Digitially through the Chancery Records Index.
  - Henry Holloway Plantation Ledger, 1796-1810
- Houff & Holler Business Records, 1904-1908, .45 cubic feet (1 box)
  Historical Information: Houff & Holler, conducted a general mercantile business in Roman, Augusta County, Virginia. The managing partners of the business were J. W. Houff and Michael Holler. The business operated for only a few years until their entire stock was consumed by fire on 1908 November 6.
  Scope and Content: Houff & Holler Business Records, 1904-1908, consists of a ledger, inventory and stock book, account book, correspondence, and receipts that record the general store's business dealings in Augusta County, Va
  Account Book, 1907, is a record of Houff & Holler's account with Planters Bank located in Bridgewater, Virginia. The book only documents deposits into the company's bank account.
  Correspondence, 1907-1908, documents Houff & Holler's business dealings with other companies. The correspondence consists primarily of solicitations from other businesses such as Sumter Telephones and Peerless Buggy Company. The businesses offer free or discounted merchandise in exchange for promotion of their items in the general store. Included in this correspondence is information from Sumter Telephones on purchasing, installing, and using their telephones. In order to promote the organization of new lines, Sumter Telephones offered their No. 356-B Mammoth 5-Bar phone complete with installation equipment for $11.25.
  Inventory and Stock Book, 1907, records the amount of goods in stock. The book includes a single entry dated 7 January 1907, which records the inventories of items such as shoes, hats, gloves, dry goods and notions, groceries, tobacco, produce, and eggs.
  Ledger, 1904-1907, records the accounts of individual customers. Each account lists transactions in chronological order. Entries include date, type of transactions, and monies debited and credited. Since most of their sales were nearly all for cash, Houff & Holler did not keep records of daily sales. The mercantile sold a variety of goods including clothing, shoes, cloth, soap, candy, eggs, sugar, coffee, beef, cigarettes, peanuts, liniment, morphine, and hardware items.
  Receipts, 1907, record the general store's accounts with other companies in Virginia. Items purchased included paint, dry goods, glassware, lamps, shoes, hardware items, and produce.
  - Houff and Holler Business Records, 1904-1908
- Breeze Johnson Ledger, 1839-1847, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Breeze Johnson, born in Virginia around 1811, was a lawyer in Staunton, Virginia.
  Scope and Content: Breeze Johnson Ledger, 1839-1847, documents the financial activities of Johnson's law firm. Transactions were entered in the accounts of individual clients. Information found in each entry includes date, type of transaction, and monies debited and credited to the account. Few details are provided as to the type of work performed for individual clients, but some accounts do contain a notation when a suit was filed in court. Scattered throughout the ledger are notations made by Johnson noting that he was to defend a client in court.
  Johnson also used the ledger to record some of the law firm's expenses. Several account entries refer to the payment of rent for office space. There are also a few account entries for the hire of servants Peyton and Thomas. It is unclear if these servants were hired slaves or free laborers. The account for Thomas notes that his service was hired at the rate of one dollar per month, and his account balance notes that he worked for Johnson for over two years. The accounts of Thomas and Peyton also describe several expenditures of the two servants. Thomas received extra cash payments, but Peyton is documented as receiving a silk vest, a white beaver hat, and an old cloth coat in addition to his cash payments.
  - Breeze Johnson Ledger, 1839-1847
- Nicholas C. Kinney Daybook and Ledgers, 1815-1830, 4 volumes
  Historical Information: Nicholas C. Kinney (1785-1859), a veteran of the War of 1812, was a lawyer in Staunton, Virginia. In 1828, Kinney was appointed as clerk of court for Augusta County. Kinney was also the owner of an 850 acre farm located in Augusta County.
  Scope and Content: Nicholas C. Kinney daybook and ledgers, 1815-1830, conists of one daybook and three ledgers largely concerning his work as a lawyer.
  - Nicholas C. Kinney Attorney Daybook, 1817-1823
    Daybook, 1817-1823, was used primarily to record the various suits that Kinney presented at court. Each entry lists the style of suit with court costs and notes the amounts of money owed and paid by his client. Throughout the volume Kinney recorded tasks he needed to accomplish. Some of these tasks relate to his cases (filing warrants, etc.) but other tasks are of a personal nature such as notes to buy candles and tobacco. The volume also contains occasional references to Kinney's farm. Kinney documented plantings and what crops were growing in certain pastures.
  - Nicholas C. Kinney Ledger, 1815-1819
    Ledger, 1815-1819, was used primarily to record the personal financial activities of Nicholas C. Kinney. Accounts are organized by the individual or company with which Kinney transacted business. Information found in each entry includes the date, type of transaction, and the monies debited or credited to the account. Most transactions concerned the lending of money and the purchase of items such as clothing, lumber, grain, and furniture. Kinney also provided cash accounts to record the cash he had on hand. Information found in these entries include the amounts paid and received along with the name of the individuals with which he did business. In addition, the back of the volume includes a list of enslaved individuals hired out in 1818, which includes: the name of the enslaved person, to whom they were hired out, and the amounts paid. Enslaved individuals mentioned by name include: Betty, Jacob, Martin, Edmund, and Obed.
  - Nicholas C. Kinney Ledger, 1823-1828
    Ledger, 1828-1830, records items purchased for Kinney's farm and his personal use. Account entries are listed chronologically and are divided into spring purchases and fall purchases. Each account is listed under the business name where the items were bought. Information found in each account entry includes a listing of the items purchased, the amounts paid for each item, and the total purchase price. Examples of items purchased include coffee, tools, hardware, tack and saddlery, cotton, stoneware, cloth, spirits, and shoes. Kinney entered the total amount of purchases at the end of each season. The final entry in the volume totals all purchases for 1828-1830.
  - Nicholas C. Kinney Account Ledger, 1828-1830
    Ledger, 1823-1828, records the financial aspects of cases tried by Kinney. Information found in each entry includes the style of suit, date of court hearing, and any court costs incurred. No indication is provided as to the nature of the case, but some entries do include amounts of debt or damages involved in the case. Some entries note that property was sold to help pay court costs. One such entry for the case of James Allen vs John Allen records the sale of a Louisa, an enslaved woman.
- Mandelbaum Clothier Daybook, 1871, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Mandelbaum Clothier, located in Staunton, Virginia, specialized in men's clothing. The clothier was also a dealer in trunks and valises. Seymore Mandelbaum, an Augusta County resident born in Virginia about 1848, was the owner and operator of the business.
  Scope and Content: Mandelbaum Clothier Daybook, 1871, records customer transaction on a daily basis as they occurred. Information found in each entry includes the name of the customer, item purchased, and the monies debited or credited to the customer's account. Customers bought such items as suits, gloves, suspenders, shoes, cologne, hats, ties, pants, and trunks.
  - Mandelbaum Clothier Daybook, 1871
- Mercer Salt Works Business Records, 1851-1856, 6 volumes
  Historical Information: The Mercer Salt Works, one of the major suppliers of salt to West Virginia, was located at the junction of New River and Lick Creek in Mercer County, West Virginia, which is now in Summers County, West Virginia. The salt works employed white laborers and hired slaves to work the furnace. Several slaves were hired from Augusta County, Va. residents, including slaves hired of Thomas J. Michie and Alexander Turk. The salt works was destroyed on 10 August 1862 by the 23rd Ohio Regiment under the command of Lieutenant Colonel Rutherford B. Hayes, who was stationed at Camp Green Meadows near the Bluestone River.
  Scope and Content: Mercer Salt Works Business Records consist of a daybook; Salt A Ledger; Ledger E; cashbook; "Wood Account and Negro Clothing" Ledger; and an account ledger.
  - Mercer Salt Works Cashbook, 1852-1856
    Cashbook, 1852-1856, records the cash received and cash disbursed on an almost daily basis. In each pair of facing book pages, the left page is used to record cash received, while the right page documents cash disbursed. Each entry includes the names of individuals or accounts that the company received cash from and paid cash to. Expenses recorded for the company include the hiring of Negroes (these entries include the owner's name but rarely was the slave's name listed), employee wages, and freight and storage costs. Also, the front of the cashbook chronicles the purchases made for 1852. Entries were arranged according to the item purchased (bacon, corn, beef) and include date of purchase, amounts bought, and amount paid.
  - Mercer Salt Works Day Book, 1851-1856
    Daybook, 1851-1856, records transactions on a daily basis as they occurred. Transactions recorded document purchases of salt and cash received to settle customer account balances. Information found in each entry includes the date and type of transaction, name of customer, and monies credited and debited to the customer's account. Each transaction was recorded under the customer's name in the corresponding Salt A Ledger. In addition, the amounts of cash received for salt on a given day were totaled and entered into the corresponding cashbook. Included in the back of the ledger is a listing of the dates that it snowed in 1853 and 1854.
  - Mercer Salt Works Ledger, 1851-1856
    Ledger, 1851-1856, records the accounts of individual employees who were either hired slaves or white laborers. Each account documents the work performed such as repairing furnace, driving cattle, etc. Wages were provided to white laborers and slaves were compensated for extra work. Both slaves and free workers were paid either in cash or goods purchased from the salt works store or from a local business. Examples of items purchased include bacon, eggs, coffee, butter, tobacco, and shoes. Many of the slave accounts were carried over from the corresponding Wood Account and Negro Clothing Ledger. Several customer accounts are also included in the ledger. These customer accounts include the amounts of salt purchased along with payments received in either cash or items bartered. The customer transactions can also be found in the corresponding daybook.
  - Mercer Salt Works Salt A Ledger, 1851-1856.
    Salt A Ledger, 1851-1856, records the accounts of individual customers. Each customer account includes separate entries for purchases and payments. Purchases were not detailed, as they were recorded in the daybook, but rather include the amount purchased, the price per unit, and the total purchase price for the transaction. However details were provided for the payments toward account balances. Mercer Salt Works accepted cash and the occasional bartered item such as tobacco for payments. Several customer accounts include notations that payments were sent out for collection, and unpaid accounts were noted with such details as "absconded" or "dead and estate insolvent." Also, company entries are recorded throughout the ledger under entries for cash accounts and produce accounts. Specific details for company expenditures can be found in the corresponding daybook and cashbook.
  - Mercer Salt Works Ledger E, 1852-1856
    Ledger E, 1852-1856, records the purchases made at the salt works' store by customers and employees. Information found in each account includes the date of transactions, merchandise purchased, and the monies debited and credited to the account. Items purchased at the store include bacon, flour, coffee, cloth, tobacco, hardware, and shoes. Customer accounts often document the salt purchases transferred to the customer's salt account which can be located in the corresponding Salt A Ledger and daybook. The Mercer Salt Works store accepted cash and bartered items (produce, livestock, eggs, etc) as payments from its customers. Several customer accounts also contain information concerning slaves hired by the salt works. For example, Thomas J. Michie's account includes a notation where Michie paid the medical bills for his slave Boston and Archibald Turk's account includes a credited amount for the hire of a "girl." Ledger E also records the purchases made by the company's employees. These employee entries are identical to the customer accounts with the exception that labor was the most prominent payment toward account balances. Employees performed such duties as working at the furnace, working at the store, driving cattle, cutting wood, etc. The employee accounts included in the ledger appear to only belong to white laborers employed at the salt works.
  - Mercer Salt Works "Wood Account and Negro Clothing" Ledger, 1851-1856
    The "Wood Account and Negro Clothing" Ledger, 1851-1856, documents the accounts of enslaved individuals hired by the salt works. Black and multiracial enslaved laborers who performed work beyond their required tasks were often compensated in cash or in goods purchased from the company's store. Individual accounts record both the work performed by ensalved laborers and items purchased by the individual with their extra wages. Each account lists transactions in chronological order and includes the date, details of the work performed or items purchased, and monies debited and credited to the account. Accounts include the enslaved person's name along with their enslavers's name. One account for "Henry Alexander's woman Susan" includes the conditions of her hire at the rate of thirty dollars and she would be "furnished the usual winter clothing" and the salt works "has the privilege of returning her at any time." Many of the entries for work performed are listed only by the number of days of work, but some entries describe the work performed. Examples of work done by enslaved laborers include cutting timber, building stables, building chimneys, and working on the furnace, and purchased items such as tobacco, coffee, clothing, hats, and boots.
    Located at the back of the volume is a record of the amounts of wood chopped by enslaved laborers for 1852 to 1856. The accounts list the namee of the enslaved individual, the name of the enslaver, the number of days worked, and the amount of wood cut. The accounts for clothing supplied to enslaved individuals were also recorded for the years 1852 to 1856, and include the enslaved person's name, the enslaver's name, and the numbers of pants, shirts, coats, shoes, boots, hats,and blankets provided for each enslaved laborer.
- Mictiow Sales Book, 1837, 1 volume
  Historical Information: This unidentified merchant operated in the Augusta County, Virginia, area during the nineteenth century and sold a variety of goods including books, clothing, and tools.
  Scope and Content: Identified on the cover as the Mictiow Sales Book, this volume documents the sale of goods made 2-7 January 1837. The sales were recorded as they occurred and were listed by the customer name and included the item purchased and the amount paid. Total sale amounts were included at the end of each day's sale. Items purchased included tools, saddlery, stoneware, gloves, shoes, clothing, perfume, and tobacco. Books were also sold and included such titles as Scott's Lessons, Tytler's History, American Psalmody, English Reader, Natural Philosophy, Village Hymns, Ladies Lexicon, Kirkham's Grammar, and Perrin's Fables.
  - Mictiow Sales Book, 1837
- Mount Ery Furnace Ledger, 1789-1793, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Mount Ery Furnace was founded by Solomon Matthews and was located in either Rockingham County or Loudoun County, Virginia. By 1793, the furnace was operated by Benjamin Fawcett and Joseph Fawcett. The furnace did business in Virginia, Maryland, and Pennsylvania during the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries.
  Scope and Content: Mount Ery Furnace Ledger, 1789-1793, records the accounts of individual customers and employees. Entries are arranged in chronological order under the account name. Entries document customer purchases of iron, but the majority of entries concern employee accounts. The employee accounts record money paid for work done, cash accounts, and items purchased such as clothing and food supplies, leather, and tobacco. Each entry includes the date of transaction, items purchased or work performed, and amount of money debited and credited.
  Also see: Augusta County Chancery Cause, Solomon Matthews vs. Benjamin Fawcett, 1828-028. Avaible Digitially through the Chancery Records Index.
  - Mount Ery Furnace Ledger, 1789-1793
- Mutual Annuity Company Ledger, 1892-1906, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Chartered in 1889, the Mutual Annuity Company operated in Augusta County, Va., during the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. In 1892, the company consolidated with Inter-states Life Association to form a single joint stock company.
  Scope and Content: The Mutual Annuity Company Ledger, 1892-1906, records the company's financial activities. The first half of the ledger is a cashbook which records the cash available on hand for 1892. The cashbook documents stock, expense fees, premiums, sundries, cash advances, postage, and expenses such as office supplies, stamps, and telegrams. Beginning in 1894, the ledger was used to keep track of individual court cases filed throughout Virginia in which the company had insured a bond or deed. Each entry is listed under the style of suit for the case and includes information such as the court in which the case was filed, the kind of interest the company held (note, deed, or bond), when the deed was dated, when the deed was due, and the amount that was insured. Some entries have comments that note how a suit was settled.
  - Mutual Annuity Company Ledger, 1892-1906
- Timothy M. Patterson General Store Ledgers, 1792-1805, 6 volumes
  Historical Information: A dealer in dry-goods, groceries, and hardware, this general store operated in the Augusta County, Virginia, area during the late eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries. Timothy M. Patterson operated the general store for the years 1798 to 1801; however, it is uncertain if Patterson controlled the general store for the entirety of its existence.
  Scope and Content: Timothy M. Patterson General Store Ledgers, 1792-1805, consists of the following six volumes: Ledger No. 4, 1792-1795; Ledger No. 5, 1795-1797; Ledger No. 6, 1789-1801; Ledger No. 7, 1802-1805; Index to Ledger No. 5, 1795-1797; and Index to Ledger No. 7, 1802-1805. The ledgers record the accounts of individual customers, with accounts carried over to the next ledger once a volume was completed. Information found in each entry includes the customer names, date of transactions, name and quantity of items purchased, amounts owed, and amounts paid. Examples of items purchased include butter, coffee, window glass, stoneware, whiskey, clothing, shoes, cloth, beef, sugar, and saddlery. The general store accepted cash, labor (making clothes, hauling, cording wood, etc), and barter (cattle, produce, etc.) as payments. Ledger No. 4 indicates that customer accounts were carried over from an unidentified Ledger No. 3. Separate indexes are included for both Ledger No. 5 and Ledger No. 7.
  - Timothy M. Patterson General Store Ledger No. 4, 1792-1795
  - Timothy M. Patterson General Store Ledger No. 5, 1795-1797
  - Index to Timothy M. Patterson General Store Ledger No. 5, 1795-1797
  - Timothy M. Patterson General Store Ledger No. 6, 1798-1801
  - Timothy M. Patterson General Store Ledger No. 7, 1802-1805
  - Index to Timothy M. Patterson General Store Ledger No. 7, 1802-1805
- Tannehill & Wheat Nursery Ledger, 1866-1874, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Tannehill & Wheat Nursery was located in Augusta County, Virginia, and was in operation during the late nineteenth century. The business was located on land that was once part of the nursery owned by the Franklin Davis Company. Joseph F. Tannehill, born in Virginia about 1830, was one of the partners of Tannehill and Wheat.